Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series I. Youth and Education
1932-1957
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.01
8.75 Linear Feet
The first series of the Thornburgh Papers includes materials from his earliest days, growing up in a suburb of Pittsburgh, and continuing through his years of education, graduating in 1957 from the University of Pittsburgh's School of Law. The files are arranged in four sections that reflect Thornburgh's academic progression: "Youth," "Mercersburg Academy," "Yale University," and "University of Pittsburgh School of Law." Included are personal items such as a childhood diary, photographs, school newspaper "Sportorials," college term papers and examinations, and all class notes and annotated texts from law school. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998.
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Rosslyn Farms (Pa.); Government; Politics; University of Pittsburgh; Education; Personal papers; University of Pittsburgh. School of Law; Yale University; Mercersburg Academy; Rossyln Farms Elementary School (Rossyln Farms, Pa.); Thornburgh, Dick -- Knowledge and learning; Thornburgh, Dick -- Childhood and youth; Thornburgh, Dick
- Youth and Education, 1932-1957; I.
  Scope and Contents note
  Dick Thornburgh grew up in Rosslyn Farms, Pennsylvania, an upper middle-class suburb of Pittsburgh. He attended Rosslyn Farms Elementary School (1937-1945), a four-room schoolhouse for kindergarten through eighth grade and where eight to ten students to a class was the norm. In 1945, Thornburgh graduated from elementary school and subsequently enjoyed only one year at Carnegie High School. Thornburgh's parents recognized that he was not being challenged academically, thus he continued his high school education at Mercersburg Academy ('50).
  Thornburgh subsequently attended Yale University ('54), majoring in engineering, although admittedly not suited to the math and science required. However, he did develop a love for writing, politics and law, and went on to earn a law degree from the University of Pittsburgh School of Law ('57). Academically Thornburgh lived up to his potential there and was soon second in his class. He earned a place on the law review, and was selected for the moot court team (Evidence, p. 11).
  These earliest files in the Thornburgh archive are remarkable in several respects. Firstly they are surprising. How many of us have saved a diary from age thirteen, "Sportorials" for the school paper, or college term papers and examinations, or class notes from graduate school? These items can be found here. Secondly, the class notes and annotated texts from law school set the stage for what became a brilliant law career, ultimately as the seventy sixth Attorney General of the United States.
  The "Youth and Education" files are in four sections: "Youth," "Mercersburg Academy," "Yale University," and "University of Pittsburgh School of Law."
  - Youth, 1932-1946; 1.
    These files are arranged chronologically and include Thornburgh's birth certificate, elementary school test scores and childhood memorabilia.
    - Birth Certificate, Baptism, Confirmation and Inoculation Records, Rosslyn Farms, PA, 1932-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Metropolitan Achievement Test Results (1939), "Public School Diploma, Allegheny County" (May 29, 1946), graduation 8th grade, 1939, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Carnegie High School, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Personal Diary, aged 13, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Family Prayer Books, 1889, 1893, 1944, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Sports team pin collection and Airplane Packet Cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mercersburg Academy, 1946-1950; 2.
    The files are arranged chronologically. Materials include composition books, memorabilia and "Sportorials." The "Sportorials" were written by Thornburgh for the Academy newspaper and are described by him as his "most fulfilling activity" while at Mercersburg (Evidence, p. 6).
    - Modern Language Course, Graduation Certificate and Memorabilia, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Sportorials" by Dick Thornburgh and articles about him, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Handwritten "English Composition Book " with essays, including "The Story of my Life", 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Yale University, 1950-1954; 3.
    Among the items here will be found: Thornburgh's acceptance of admission letter from Yale, class notebooks, research papers, copies of The Yale Record, sports and theatre programs, memorabilia and diary from Thornburgh's 1953 trip to Europe. Some post-graduation alumni items have also been included here.
    - Memorabilia including Yale acceptance letter and transcript of all four years, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Playbills and Programs, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Drama productions, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Promenades", 1952, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Football programs, 1950-1951, 1953, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Basketball and swimming programs, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - " '54 ": a Yale Banner Publication, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "The Yale Record", September, 1950-October, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Papers and research: Flood Control, Pittsburgh and History of Pennsylvania Turnpike, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - "Flood Control-Pittsburgh, PA", 1954
      - "The Pennsylvania Turnpike--Harrisburg to Pittsburgh: America's First 'Dream Highway'", 1954
    - Paper: "Surgoinsville Hydro-Electric Project, Holston River, TN", 1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Baccalaureate and Commencement Programs, June 6-7, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Papers and exams: Structural Engineering, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - The Robert A. Taft Memorial Lecture Series, Watertown, CT, February 24, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Notebook: Yale Engineering Camp, East Lyme, CT, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Class Notebooks, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
    - Class Notes and Textbook: "History of Art", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Class Notebook: Civil Engineering "Water Supply", January, 1954-June, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Quizzes, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "The Yankanuck Song Book", ca. 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Trip to Europe Memorabilia, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Trip to Europe Memorabilia and trip diary, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Post Graduation; 25th Reunion 1979, articles (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - University of Pittsburgh School of Law, 1954-1957; 4.
    The papers are arranged chronologically and consist of four sections: 1) notes, reports and memorabilia; 2) Law Reviews and anniversary publication; 3) handwritten class notebooks; and 4) Thornburgh's annotated textbooks. Publications in the second section consist of The University of Pittsburgh Law Review (1954-1957) as well as Pitt Magazine's coverage of the seventy fifth anniversary of the Law School (1970). The Class notebooks section rather remarkably consists of twenty-two handwritten notebooks from each law school class, every semester. Of particular interest, too, are textbooks with his annotations, and one with a fetching pin-up picture inside the cover.
    - Notes, Reports and Memorabilia
      - Memorabilia especially including "Recollections About Ginny" (2004 bio of Thornburgh's first wife, Virginia Hooton Thornburgh), 1954-1957, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - School transcript, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Moot Law Court: notes and research, Fall, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Common Pleas case: Ralph Wilson vs. Pennsylvania Railroad Co., Thornburgh et al attorneys, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Supreme Court Case: Leopard Oil Co. Inc. vs. Superoil Corp., 1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Federal Case: DeEugenio vs. Allis Chalmers, pre-trial notes, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Federal Case: DeEugenio vs. Allis Chalmers, Thornburgh et al attorneys, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Non Law Review Award, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Class of 1957 parody photographs (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Secretary, Class of 1957: Alumni Funds, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - 1967 "Who's Who" Class of 1957 and notes, October, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - 1972 and 1997 "Who's Who" Class of 1957, October 21, 1972, September 12-14, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Lawyer's Register, no. 151 first edition, July, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Exams, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence regarding Board of Law Examiners and 1957 passage of bar exam, 1955-1958 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Selective Service Form and Letter to the Draft Board, April 29, 1957, October 4, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - School of Law Publications
      - University of Pittsburgh Law Review, v. 16 nos. 1-4, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - University of Pittsburgh Law Review, v. 17 nos. 1, 2, and 3, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - University of Pittsburgh Law Review, v. 18 nos. 2 and 4, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Pitt Magazine: The School of Law's 75th Anniversary, v. 26, no. 2, Summer, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Class Notebooks
      - Torts, Fall, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Property, Fall, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Contracts, Fall, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Legislative Process, Fall, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Criminal Law, Spring, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Constitutional Law, Fall, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Equity, Fall, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Property II, Fall, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Evidence, Fall, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Negotiable Instruments, Fall, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Corporations, Fall, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Suretyship, Spring, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Descendant's Estates, Spring, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Property II, Spring, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Trusts, Fall, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Taxation, Fall, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Future Interests, Fall, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Common Pleas, Fall, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Conflicts, Spring, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Taxation II, Spring, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Labor, Spring, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Sales, Spring, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Thornburgh's Annotated Textbooks
      - Fraser's Cases and Readings on Property: Introduction (pinup picture), 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Cases and Materials on Criminal Law and Procedure, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Cases and Materials on Real Property and Conveyancing, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Cases and Materials on the Law of Sales and Sales Financing, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Fraser's Case and Readings on Personal Property, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Cases on Labor Law, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Case Materials on Future Interests, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Cases on Equity, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Cases on Wills and Administration, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - A Selection of Cases on the Law of Contracts, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Cases and Materials on Legislation, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Purdon's Pennsylvania Statutes Annotated, Permanent Edition: Title 12A Uniform Commercial Code 1-101 to 3-806, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Purdon's Pennsylvania Statutes Annotated, Permanent Edition: Title 12A Uniform Commercial Code 4-101 to End, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Cases on the Law of Bills and Notes, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Cases and Materials on the Law of Corporations, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Cases and Materials on the Law of Credit Transactions, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Cases and Other Materials on the Law of Taxation, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Notes found inside Cases on Agency, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Cases on Agency, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - A Preliminary Survey of the Law of Real Property, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Cases and Materials on Constitutional Law, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Cases on Torts, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Inserts and notes found in Cases and Other Materials on Civil Procedure, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Cases and Other Materials on Civil Procedure, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Pennsylvania Common Pleas Practice: Statutes, Rules, Forms and Cases, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Cases and Materials on the Law of Evidence, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Report of the Joint State Government Commission of the General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Relating to the Following: Descendants' Estates Laws Fiduciaries Act of 1949 Fiduciaries Investment Act of 1949, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Report of the Joint State Government Commission of the General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Relating to the Following: Descendants' Estates Laws Interstate Act of 1947, Wills Act of 1947, Principal and Income Act of 1947, dated 1951, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Select Cases and Other Authorities on the Law of Trusts, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Conflict of Laws: Cases and Materials, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Statutory Supplement to Cases on Labor Law, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 11)